Hello everyone.
안녕하세요, 여러분.
I hope you all had a good DevOps and that you still have some energy left for the last
여러분 모두 좋은 데브옵스를 보냈기를 바라며, 마지막까지 에너지가 남아 있기를 바랍니다.
talk.
이야기.
I do.
I want a better way to start off a talk than with a little story, a tale, an anecdote.
작은 이야기나 일화, 일화로 강연을 시작하는 것보다 더 좋은 방법은 없습니다.
Some years ago I joined a new company and with that I joined a new team.
몇 년 전 저는 새로운 회사에 입사했고 그와 함께 새로운 팀에 합류했습니다.
And the team itself was a newly formed team within that company.
그리고 그 팀 자체도 그 회사 내에서 새로 구성된 팀이었습니다.
And we received a new project.
그리고 새로운 프로젝트를 받았습니다.
Although the project itself was not a new project, it was actually an existing project
프로젝트 자체는 새 프로젝트가 아니었지만 실제로는 기존 프로젝트였습니다.
that was actively developed on by another team in another country even.
심지어 다른 나라의 다른 팀에서 활발히 개발 중이던 프로젝트였습니다.
And the project itself just received its first production release.
그리고 프로젝트 자체는 이제 막 첫 번째 프로덕션 릴리스를 받았습니다.
So actual customers could use it in production.
그래서 실제 고객이 프로덕션에서 사용할 수 있게 되었습니다.
And to ease over the transition, they...
그리고 전환을 쉽게 하기 위해...
Oh, sorry.
오, 죄송합니다.
So the management decided that the project should move from one team abroad to the newly
그래서 경영진은 프로젝트를 해외의 한 팀에서 새로 온 팀으로 옮기기로 결정했습니다.
formed team.
팀을 구성했습니다.
And to ease over the transition, they decided to install some handover days.
인수인계 기간을 설정하여 인수인계가 원활하게 이루어지도록 했습니다.
So both teams got together and we learned about the application, the domain, the technical
그래서 두 팀이 함께 모여 애플리케이션, 도메인, 기술에 대해 배웠습니다.
side of things.
측면에 대해 배웠죠.
And we quickly noticed something.
그리고 우리는 금방 뭔가를 알아챘습니다.
We couldn't find any tests.
어떤 테스트도 찾을 수 없었습니다.
So naturally we went to the other team and asked, like, where are the tests?
그래서 자연스럽게 다른 팀에 가서 테스트가 어디 있냐고 물었습니다.
And they responded by saying, well, there are no tests.
그러자 그들은 테스트가 없다고 대답했습니다.
We don't write tests.
우리는 테스트를 작성하지 않습니다.
That's weird, right?
이상하지 않나요?
Why wouldn't you write tests?
왜 테스트를 작성하지 않죠?
And they answered by saying, well, we don't write tests because we don't write bugs.
그리고 그들은 버그를 작성하지 않기 때문에 테스트를 작성하지 않는다고 대답했습니다.
And this is exactly what this talk is about.
그리고 이것이 바로 이 강연의 주제입니다.
Why would you write tests?
왜 테스트를 작성하나요?
How do you test that?
어떻게 테스트하나요?
And I can assure you that the answer to the first question, why do you write tests, is
그리고 첫 번째 질문인 왜 테스트를 작성하는지에 대한 답은 다음과 같다고 확신할 수 있습니다.
not simply because we all write bugs.
단순히 우리 모두가 버그를 작성하기 때문이 아닙니다.
In a way, this story is a bit sad, a bit arrogant, and marginally funny.
어떻게 보면 이 이야기는 약간 슬프고, 약간 오만하고, 약간 웃기기도 합니다.
But if I reflect upon myself and my own ideas and concepts around testing, I can't say that
하지만 테스트에 대한 제 자신과 제 생각과 개념을 되돌아보면, 저는 이렇게 말할 수 없습니다.
they've been that great either all the time.
항상 그렇게 훌륭했다고 말할 수는 없습니다.
And to illustrate that, I would like to go back in time yet again.
이를 설명하기 위해 다시 한 번 시간을 거슬러 올라가 보겠습니다.
And this time to the beginning of time.
이번에는 태초로 돌아갑니다.
To that moment I first started working as a developer.
제가 처음 개발자로 일하기 시작한 그 순간까지.
I don't know for you guys, but for me, it was quite daunting.
여러분은 어떨지 모르겠지만 저에게는 꽤나 벅찬 순간이었습니다.
You have to imagine, this was a world without Spring Boot.
스프링 부트가 없는 세상이었다고 상상해 보세요.
If you had a Spring project, you were lucky.
스프링 프로젝트가 있었다면 운이 좋았습니다.
Because else you had to fight off dragons like EGB and kill monsters like OSGI, struts.
그렇지 않으면 EGB와 같은 드래곤과 싸우고 OSGI, 스트럿츠와 같은 괴물을 죽여야 했으니까요.
But in any case, I managed.
어쨌든 난 해냈어.
But unlike that other team, I was introduced to a team back then that wrote tests.
하지만 다른 팀과 달리 저는 그때 테스트를 작성하는 팀을 소개받았습니다.
So from day one, I was exposed to testing.
그래서 첫날부터 저는 테스트에 노출되었습니다.
But to be honest, my focus was not really on writing tests.
하지만 솔직히 말해서 저는 테스트 작성에 집중하지 않았습니다.
I was very much focused on writing production code.
저는 프로덕션 코드를 작성하는 데 매우 집중했습니다.
The young developer that I was, was already happy if the code just worked.
젊은 개발자였던 저는 코드가 작동하기만 하면 이미 행복했습니다.
And naturally, I wrote the tests because I had to.
당연히 테스트를 작성해야 했기 때문에 테스트를 작성했습니다.
Like I said, it was not my focus.
말씀드렸듯이 제 초점은 그게 아니었습니다.
So in that moment in time, I kind of assumed that I had to write tests
그래서 그 순간 저는 테스트를 작성해야 한다고 생각했습니다.
simply to verify the correctness of the code.
단순히 코드의 정확성을 확인하기 위해서요.
In the moment, at the moment you're writing your test, in that little window.
지금 이 순간, 여러분이 테스트를 작성하는 순간, 그 작은 창에서.
But then time goes on and you grow as a developer, right?
하지만 시간이 흐르고 개발자로서 성장하게 되죠?
You go to conferences, read books.
컨퍼런스에 참석하고 책을 읽어요.
And you start to realize there's actually much more to testing than simply verifying correctness.
그리고 테스트에는 단순히 정확성을 확인하는 것 이상의 의미가 있다는 것을 깨닫기 시작합니다.
For one, it helps you prevent regression.
우선, 회귀를 방지하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
We all know what it is, right?
우리 모두 그게 뭔지 아시죠?
Now, one project, we were constantly battling regression.
한 프로젝트에서 우리는 끊임없이 회귀와 싸웠습니다.
Why? Because we were unable to refactor our code.
왜 그랬을까요? 코드를 리팩터링할 수 없었기 때문입니다.
You know how it goes, right?
어떻게 되는지 아시죠?
You receive a project, a completely new one.
완전히 새로운 프로젝트를 받습니다.
And every developer, every team has certain ideas on style or how to do things.
모든 개발자, 모든 팀은 스타일이나 작업 방식에 대한 특정 아이디어를 가지고 있습니다.
So we wanted to apply our style to that project.
그래서 저희는 그 프로젝트에 저희 스타일을 적용하고 싶었습니다.
We wanted to do things our way.
우리 방식대로 하고 싶었어요.
We quickly halted that because, yeah, we were causing regression.
우리는 퇴보를 일으키고 있었기 때문에 재빨리 중단했습니다.
We were unable to refactor freely in a safe way.
안전한 방법으로 자유롭게 리팩터링할 수 없었습니다.
Tests allow us to evolve our system at a steady pace.
테스트를 통해 꾸준한 속도로 시스템을 발전시킬 수 있습니다.
And that is so much more than simply verifying the correctness of code.
테스트는 단순히 코드의 정확성을 검증하는 것 이상의 의미가 있습니다.
Now, one system we received was unable to evolve, was hard to evolve.
이제 우리가 받은 한 시스템은 진화할 수 없었고, 진화하기 어려웠습니다.
Even to the point that management started to ask questions like,
심지어 경영진이 다음과 같은 질문을 하기 시작할 정도였습니다,
what is going on, guys?
무슨 일이야, 얘들아?
Now, one team never had any issues with them.
한 팀은 아무런 문제가 없었습니다.
And you guys, if you ship anything, you break things constantly.
그리고 너희들은 뭐든 배송하면 끊임없이 물건을 망가뜨리잖아.
What management didn't realize, for one, is that, yeah, the project just went live.
경영진이 깨닫지 못한 것은 프로젝트가 방금 시작되었다는 사실입니다.
So the time that the other team had to develop it, the project was not really used.
그래서 다른 팀이 개발해야 하는 시간 동안 프로젝트는 실제로 사용되지 않았습니다.
And another thing was, they didn't write tests.
그리고 또 한 가지, 그들은 테스트를 작성하지 않았습니다.
So, yeah, naturally, when you don't write tests, your speed, your velocity will be high.
테스트를 작성하지 않으면 당연히 속도가 빨라지겠죠.
What will happen inevitably is it will plummet down.
필연적으로 일어날 일은 급락하는 것입니다.
You will have to fight regression.
퇴행과 싸워야 할 것입니다.
You will be unable to evolve your system.
시스템을 진화시킬 수 없게 됩니다.
What tests give you is the evolvability at a steady pace.
테스트 결과 꾸준한 속도로 진화할 수 있습니다.
It allows us to go forward indefinitely.
무한히 앞으로 나아갈 수 있습니다.
Yes, that initial curve will be a bit steeper.
예, 초기 곡선이 조금 더 가파르게 됩니다.
When we received the project, it didn't come with any kind of documentation.
프로젝트를 받았을 때 어떤 종류의 문서도 함께 제공되지 않았습니다.
And those few days of handover weren't merely enough to really grasp the system itself.
며칠간의 인수인계만으로는 시스템 자체를 파악하기에 충분하지 않았습니다.
And afterwards, the other team was also not really...
그리고 그 후, 다른 팀도 정말...
was quite reluctant to answer our questions.
우리의 질문에 대답하기를 꺼려했습니다.
So we were left in the dark a bit sometimes.
그래서 우리는 가끔 어둠 속에 남겨졌습니다.
And there were no tests.
그리고 테스트가 없었습니다.
Because if there were tests, we could start reading them.
테스트가 있었다면 읽을 수 있었을 테니까요.
Because tests actually define the boundaries of our system, right?
테스트는 실제로 우리 시스템의 경계를 정의하기 때문이죠?
They tell us what falls in and what falls out.
테스트는 무엇이 들어가고 무엇이 나가는지 알려주죠.
And they're actually much more than those stale pieces of documentation
그리고 그들은 실제로 오래된 문서 조각보다 훨씬 더 많습니다.
we sometimes have to write on wikis, which start to drift from our code.
가끔은 위키에 글을 써야 할 때가 있는데, 코드에서 벗어나기 시작하죠.
They're living pieces of documentation.
위키야말로 살아있는 문서입니다.
Because if I have to write a feature, I write a test for that.
기능을 작성해야 한다면 그에 대한 테스트를 작성하기 때문이죠.
If I alter that feature, and I don't alter that test, in theory, my build should fail.
만약 내가 그 기능을 변경하고 테스트를 변경하지 않는다면 이론적으로 내 빌드는 실패해야 한다.
So we're forced to update our tests.
그래서 테스트를 업데이트해야 합니다.
They're executable pieces of documentation.
실행 가능한 문서입니다.
Again, much more than simply verifying correctness.
다시 말하지만, 단순히 정확성을 확인하는 것 이상입니다.
They guide our design.
디자인에 지침이 됩니다.
TDD, right?
TDD 맞죠?
It's very much at the forefront of this, where you first write your test,
테스트를 처음 작성할 때 가장 중요한 부분입니다,
then you write the simplest implementation possible,
그리고 나서 가능한 가장 간단한 구현을 작성합니다,
and then you refactor over it until the design is good enough for you, beautiful.
그런 다음 디자인이 마음에 들 때까지 리팩터링합니다.
We all know that code that is hard to test is often smelly.
테스트하기 어려운 코드는 종종 냄새가 난다는 것을 우리 모두 알고 있습니다.
There's something wrong with the design, right?
디자인에 뭔가 문제가 있는 거죠?
Code should be easy to test.
코드는 테스트하기 쉬워야 합니다.
Let tests guide you.
테스트가 여러분을 안내합니다.
And all these traits, these good traits of tests together,
그리고 이 모든 특성들, 테스트의 좋은 특성들을 함께,
allow us to continuously release with confidence.
자신감을 가지고 지속적으로 출시할 수 있습니다.
Because that's what I want to be as a developer.
그것이 제가 개발자로서 원하는 것이기 때문입니다.
I want to feel safe.
안전하다고 느끼고 싶어요.
I want to be able to ship my product on a Friday evening and go home.
금요일 저녁에 제품을 배송하고 집에 갈 수 있기를 원합니다.
And then time goes on, and when I learned all these things,
그리고 시간이 지나고 이 모든 것을 알게 되었을 때,
I thought that testing is great.
테스트는 정말 대단하다고 생각했어요.
But when I looked around, I found that the reality of tests
하지만 주위를 둘러보니 테스트의 현실은 다음과 같았습니다.
was sometimes a bit different.
는 때때로 조금 달랐습니다.
I found tests to be brittle sometimes.
가끔 테스트가 깨지는 경우가 있습니다.
Simply adding a dependency, changing a parameter,
종속성을 추가하고 매개변수를 변경하기만 하면 됩니다,
just reshaping the code, not really changing the behavior,
코드를 재구성하는 것일 뿐, 동작을 변경하는 것은 아닙니다,
but just the shape of the code would break tests.
코드의 모양만 바꾸면 테스트가 중단됩니다.
Sometimes in remote places of the code base.
코드 베이스의 외진 곳에 있을 때도 있습니다.
Sometimes I found tests to be really, really complex
가끔 테스트가 정말, 정말 복잡하다는 것을 알았습니다.
for relatively simple production code.
비교적 간단한 프로덕션 코드의 경우.
Hence they were hard to maintain.
따라서 유지 관리가 어려웠습니다.
They did not guide.
그들은 안내하지 않았다.
TDD is a bit like teenage sex.
TDD는 십대 섹스와 비슷하다.
Everyone's talking about it, but who's actually doing it?
다들 얘기하지만 실제로 하는 사람은 누구일까요?
Sometimes I found tests to be cryptic.
가끔은 테스트가 모호하다는 걸 알았어요.
I encountered tests and I had no clue
테스트를 만났는데 전혀 알 수 없었습니다.
by the test method name what was being actually tested.
테스트 방법 이름으로 실제로 무엇을 테스트하고 있는지 알 수 없었습니다.
Not only if I read the body of the method,
메서드 본문을 읽었을 때뿐만 아니라,
and sometimes even worse, the test method said one thing,
그리고 때로는 테스트 방법에서 한 가지를 더 나쁘게 말했습니다,
okay, great, you read the body and it said something else.
좋아, 좋아, 본문을 읽었는데 다른 걸 말했어.
So either one of the two is lying or we need two tests.
둘 중 하나가 거짓말이거나 두 가지 테스트가 필요해.
And sometimes they were horrendously slow.
그리고 가끔은 끔찍하게 느렸어요.
I worked once in a team and they found it completely normal
한 팀에서 일한 적이 있는데 완전히 정상이라고 하더군요.
that the test time was one hour for a rather small application.
테스트 시간이 다소 작은 애플리케이션의 경우 한 시간이었습니다.
And the worst of all, like that one team, skipping testing.
그리고 최악의 경우, 저 팀처럼 테스트를 건너뛰는 경우도 있었습니다.
So surely the benefits of writing tests,
테스트 작성의 이점은 분명합니다,
running and maintaining them should outweigh the cost.
테스트를 실행하고 유지하는 데 드는 비용보다 더 큰 이점이 있을 겁니다.
And I think there's a kind of paradox going on here
그리고 여기에는 일종의 역설이 있다고 생각합니다.
because at one hand, most developers really value testing.
한편으로는 대부분의 개발자가 테스트를 정말 중요하게 생각하기 때문이죠.
They really think testing is important,
개발자들은 테스트가 정말 중요하다고 생각합니다,
but that is seldom reflected in the test code.
하지만 테스트 코드에는 거의 반영되지 않습니다.
And there's another paradox going on here, on a code level,
그리고 코드 수준에서 또 다른 역설이 벌어지고 있습니다,
because most developers really care about the code,
대부분의 개발자는 코드에 정말 관심이 많기 때문입니다,
they're meticulous about it.
꼼꼼하기 때문이죠.
We're all about clean code, right?
우리 모두 깔끔한 코드가 중요하죠?
At least that's for the production code.
적어도 프로덕션 코드에 대해서는요.
The test code seems to be different.
테스트 코드가 다른 것 같습니다.
I find that a paradox.
역설적이네요.
And the last paradox I identified was on an architectural level,
그리고 제가 마지막으로 발견한 역설은 건축 수준에서 발견했습니다,
because architecture is all around us, right?
건축은 우리 주변에 있잖아요, 그렇죠?
No application is designed without considering architecture somehow.
아키텍처를 고려하지 않고 설계된 애플리케이션은 없습니다.
We create diagrams, C4, architectural decision records.
다이어그램, C4, 아키텍처 결정 기록을 작성합니다.
We have people walking around in the office calling themselves an architect,
사무실에서 스스로를 건축가라고 칭하며 돌아다니는 사람들이 있습니다,
and it doesn't stop there.
그리고 거기서 멈추지 않습니다.
We have different types of architects,
우리에게는 다양한 유형의 건축가가 있습니다,
solution, enterprise, application architects.
솔루션, 엔터프라이즈, 애플리케이션 아키텍트.
But all of this architecture we do is for our production code.
하지만 우리가 하는 이 모든 아키텍처는 프로덕션 코드를 위한 것입니다.
Seldom, rarely we turn around and look at the test code.
뒤돌아서서 테스트 코드를 살펴보는 경우는 거의 없습니다.
Because then I question myself,
그러면 스스로에게 의문이 들기 때문입니다,
like, don't we find our test important to be considered?
우리 테스트가 중요하다고 생각하지 않나요?
Because that is for me what architecture is about,
그게 바로 아키텍처의 본질이니까요,
the important stuff.
중요한 것들.
Also our tests.
테스트도요.
And when we're doing architecture, we're constantly making trade-offs.
아키텍처를 만들 때는 끊임없이 절충점을 찾아야 합니다.
When our tests are slow, when our tests are brittle,
테스트가 느릴 때, 테스트가 취약할 때,
or hard to maintain, there were trade-offs there that we didn't make.
유지 관리가 어려울 때는 우리가 생각하지 못한 트레이드오프가 있었습니다.
And we constantly make them in our production code.
그리고 저희는 프로덕션 코드에서 지속적으로 이를 개선하고 있습니다.
Architecture guides us.
아키텍처가 우리를 안내합니다.
If I start working on an existing project that I don't know,
내가 모르는 기존 프로젝트에서 작업을 시작하면,
I often reside to the architectural diagrams, the ADRs, stuff like that,
저는 종종 아키텍처 다이어그램이나 ADR 같은 것들에 상주합니다,
to really understand what is the meaning of the architecture.
아키텍처의 의미를 제대로 이해하기 위해요.
But that's always for the production code.
하지만 이는 항상 프로덕션 코드에 대한 것입니다.
The test code, there's nothing.
테스트 코드에는 아무것도 없습니다.
So I start to wonder, like, how did we end up here?
그래서 어떻게 여기까지 왔을까 궁금해지기 시작합니다.
Why is this happening?
왜 이런 일이 벌어지는 거지?
And I think a lot of it stems from that initial premise I said
그리고 많은 부분이 제가 처음에 말한 전제에서 비롯된 것 같아요.
at the beginning of my career.
제 경력을 시작할 때요.
That we're so focused in the moment, when you're writing production code,
프로덕션 코드를 작성하는 순간에 집중할 수 있습니다,
because that's the task at hand, right?
당면한 일이니까요, 그렇죠?
That's what you get paid for.
그게 바로 돈을 받는 이유죠.
It's very hard to leave that moment.
그 순간을 떠나기가 정말 힘들어요.
And you do not only write a test in the current moment,
그리고 지금 이 순간에만 테스트를 작성하는 것이 아닙니다,
for the current moment, simply to verify correctness.
현재 순간에 대한 테스트를 단순히 정확성을 확인하기 위해 작성하는 것이 아닙니다.
That's only part of the story.
이것은 이야기의 일부일 뿐입니다.
So let's try to answer the three W's.
이제 세 가지 W에 대해 대답해 봅시다.
And let's start with, why do we write tests?
먼저 왜 테스트를 작성할까요?
Well, I think we write tests to cope with change.
글쎄요, 변화에 대처하기 위해 테스트를 작성하는 것 같아요.
Because requirements change.
요구사항이 변하기 때문이죠.
Integrations change.
통합이 변경되었습니다.
Security, technology, data formats, deployment methods,
보안, 기술, 데이터 형식, 배포 방법,
people and organizations themselves change.
사람과 조직 자체가 변화합니다.
And let me give you an example of change.
변화의 예를 들어보겠습니다.
I once had to work on a system, and it was an existing system.
한 번은 시스템 작업을 해야 했는데, 기존 시스템이었어요.
And it was actually developed a decade ago.
사실 10년 전에 개발되었죠.
And the task was very simple.
그리고 작업은 매우 간단했습니다.
They finally decided to kick out that COBOL mainframe.
마침내 COBOL 메인프레임을 쫓아내기로 결정했습니다.
And everybody who was talking to that COBOL mainframe
그리고 그 COBOL 메인프레임과 대화하던 모든 사람들은
had to now talk to the cloud.
이제 클라우드와 대화해야 했습니다.
So they found a cloud solution to replace COBOL.
그래서 그들은 COBOL을 대체할 클라우드 솔루션을 찾았습니다.
And my job was simply to not change the requirements in this case,
그리고 제 임무는 이 경우 요구 사항을 변경하지 않는 것이었습니다,
but change the integration.
통합을 변경하는 것입니다.
I had to make sure that that system was able to talk to the cloud.
해당 시스템이 클라우드와 통신할 수 있는지 확인해야 했습니다.
And when I went along implementing this,
그리고 구현을 진행하면서
I looked at the commit logs, and I found interesting things.
커밋 로그를 살펴보니 흥미로운 것을 발견했습니다.
Yes, the first two years, there were a lot of requirements
네, 처음 2년 동안은 많은 요구사항이 있었습니다.
being built and added.
구축되고 추가되었습니다.
But then it kind of halted, and it was like a void.
그런데 갑자기 멈춰버렸어요. 마치 공허한 느낌이었죠.
And then I found security patches.
그러다 보안 패치를 찾았어요.
I found that people, I found that they were deploying the application
사람들이 애플리케이션을 배포하는 것을 발견했습니다.
as a WAR file first, deployment methods.
WAR 파일로 먼저 배포하는 것을 발견했습니다.
And then they kind of switched to a JAR, Spring Boot, one, two.
그리고 나서 JAR, Spring Boot, 하나, 둘로 전환했습니다.
And while I was there, I decided, let's go for three then.
거기 있는 동안 저는 세 개로 가자고 결정했습니다.
And I also found that, hey, in the beginning,
그리고 처음에 이런 것도 발견했어요,
they were deploying it as a WAR in an application server.
애플리케이션 서버에 WAR로 배포하고 있었습니다.
And in this point in time, they were deploying it
그리고 이 시점에, 그들은 그것을 배포하고 있었습니다.
in the cloud, Kubernetes.
클라우드인 쿠버네티스에 배포하고 있었습니다.
I also found that throughout that decade, dozens of people
또한 그 10년 동안 수십 명의 사람들이
have committed and worked on that.
헌신하고 노력했습니다.
Even people, I asked my colleague, who's Mark?
심지어 사람들에게도 마크가 누구냐고 물어봤어요.
He said, I have never met Mark here.
그는 말하길, 나는 여기서 마크를 만난 적이 없다고 했다.
Things constantly change, and that is why we test.
상황은 끊임없이 변하기 때문에 우리는 테스트한다.
And that's the key characteristic of software, change.
이것이 바로 소프트웨어의 핵심 특성인 변화입니다.
And tests allow us to change things.
그리고 테스트를 통해 우리는 무언가를 바꿀 수 있습니다.
Tests are change enablers.
테스트는 변화를 가능하게 합니다.
Other things in software are obviously also important.
소프트웨어의 다른 것들도 분명히 중요합니다.
But if you're unable to change a thing,
하지만 하나도 바꿀 수 없다면,
you will never make it faster, more secure, resilient,
더 빠르고, 더 안전하고, 더 탄력적으로 만들 수 없습니다,
whatever you want it to be.
당신이 원하는 대로.
And tests gave us that ability.
그리고 테스트를 통해 그 능력을 얻었습니다.
And that is so much more than simply verifying correctness.
그리고 그것은 단순히 정확성을 검증하는 것 이상의 의미가 있습니다.
So the reason for writing tests is change, adaptability,
그래서 테스트를 작성하는 이유는 변화와 적응력입니다,
to evolve.
진화하기 위해서죠.
What do we actually test?
실제로 무엇을 테스트하나요?
What is the system under test?
테스트 중인 시스템은 무엇인가요?
And let's go back again in time to that younger version
다시 시간을 거슬러 더 어린 버전으로 돌아가 봅시다.
of myself and ask this question.
나 자신의 모습을 떠올리며 이 질문을 해보죠.
I think I would have answered something in the lines of,
저는 이런 식으로 대답했을 것 같아요,
well, you asked me to write production code.
프로덕션 코드를 작성하라고 하셨잖아요.
That's the job at hand, right?
그게 지금 할 일이지?
So I write code, and I write test code to test the code.
그래서 코드를 작성하고, 코드를 테스트하기 위해 테스트 코드를 작성합니다.
So I'm kind of testing the code.
그래서 코드를 테스트하고 있습니다.
That's what I'm testing, obviously.
물론 제가 테스트하고 있는 것은 이것입니다.
And that's true.
그리고 그건 사실입니다.
You can't say it's not right.
옳지 않다고 할 수는 없지.
You are testing the code.
코드를 테스트하고 있습니다.
But you are testing that implicitly.
하지만 암시적으로 테스트하고 있습니다.
What you want to test explicitly is something else.
명시적으로 테스트하고 싶은 것은 다른 것입니다.
So let's answer the following question first.
그럼 먼저 다음 질문에 답해봅시다.
What do we actually write code for?
우리는 실제로 무엇을 위해 코드를 작성할까요?
And I'm a bit of a geek.
그리고 난 좀 괴짜거든.
I really don't need any reasons to write code.
저는 코드를 작성할 이유가 정말 필요 없어요.
I just love solving puzzles.
난 그냥 퍼즐을 푸는 게 좋아.
I don't need business value.
난 사업적 가치는 필요없어.
But surely that's not the case, right?
하지만 그렇지 않죠?
Why do we all write code?
우리 모두는 왜 코드를 작성할까요?
We write code because there's someone who has a pack of money.
우리는 돈을 많이 가진 사람이 있기 때문에 코드를 작성합니다.
Let's be honest.
솔직해지자.
And that someone wants a system to behave in a certain way.
그리고 누군가는 시스템이 특정 방식으로 작동하기를 원합니다.
He has a requirement for a system to behave.
그는 시스템 작동에 대한 요구 사항을 가지고 있다.
That's why we write code.
그래서 코드를 작성합니다.
We don't write code for code.
우리는 코드를 위한 코드를 작성하지 않습니다.
When I was young, in the beginning of my career,
어렸을 때, 경력 초기에,
I often had this false assumption.
저는 종종 이런 잘못된 가정을 했었습니다.
That was my trigger for writing tests.
이것이 제가 테스트를 작성하게 된 계기가 되었습니다.
This comes from a really good talk by Ian Cooper.
이 말은 이안 쿠퍼의 훌륭한 강연에서 따왔어요.
But the trigger for writing a test is not a new class.
하지만 테스트를 작성하는 트리거는 새로운 클래스가 아닙니다.
Not a new public method.
새로운 공용 메서드가 아닙니다.
That was something I was constantly doing.
제가 계속 하던 일이었습니다.
I was writing a new public method.
새로운 공개 메서드를 작성하고 있었다.
And I thought, like, let's write a class for that.
그래서 저는 이를 위한 클래스를 작성해보자고 생각했습니다.
I was very much driven by this idea of code coverage.
저는 코드 커버리지에 대한 아이디어에 이끌렸습니다.
I thought I was doing good.
잘하고 있다고 생각했어요.
And I was doing good.
난 잘하고 있었다.
But I think we can do better.
하지만 더 잘할 수 있을 것 같아.
So what is the trigger then?
그럼 트리거가 뭐죠?
Well, the trigger is behavior.
트리거는 행동입니다.
And to a lesser extent, the code, as we'll see later.
그리고 그보다 덜 중요한 것은 나중에 살펴보겠지만 코드입니다.
But the main trigger for most people,
하지만 대부분의 사람들에게 주요 트리거는
for most business application, oriented application,
대부분의 비즈니스 응용 프로그램, 지향 응용 프로그램의 경우,
is the behavior, not the code.
는 코드가 아니라 동작입니다.
And you should test your behavioral contract,
그리고 행동 계약을 테스트해야 합니다,
whatever that means technically.
기술적으로 무슨 뜻인지 모르겠지만.
And the last sentence is quite important.
그리고 마지막 문장이 아주 중요합니다.
Because when I'm in the office and talking
왜냐면 제가 사무실에서 얘기할 때
about this behavioral stuff, sometimes colleagues come to me
이런 행동에 대해 동료들이 가끔 저에게 찾아와서
and they tell me, you probably only want
그리고 그들은 나에게 말하죠, 당신은 아마
us to write integration tests.
통합 테스트를 작성하라고 합니다.
And then we'll just capture the behavior.
그리고 나서 동작을 캡처합니다.
No.
아니요.
I didn't imply that.
그런 뜻은 아니었어.
When I'm saying test the behavior,
내가 동작을 테스트하라고 했을 때,
I don't imply any type of test.
나는 어떤 유형의 테스트를 암시하지 않습니다.
That's a different thing.
그건 다른 문제입니다.
You should not confuse that.
혼동하지 마세요.
And when we're talking about the different types of tests,
그리고 다른 유형의 테스트에 대해 이야기할 때,
integration tests, or unit tests,
통합 테스트 또는 단위 테스트,
it's interesting to take a look at the ancient pyramid.
고대 피라미드를 살펴보는 것은 흥미롭습니다.
And I question, is this still relevant?
이게 아직도 의미가 있을까?
And what are the alternatives?
대안은 무엇인가요?
We all know this pyramid, right?
우리 모두 이 피라미드를 알고 있죠?
Like at the bottom, we write lots and lots
아래에서와 같이, 우리는 로트와 로트를 씁니다.
of fast and cheap unit tests.
빠르고 저렴한 단위 테스트의
And above that, layer above, we write
그리고 그 위에 다음과 같이 작성합니다.
lesser, fewer integration tests, which
더 적은 수의 통합 테스트, 즉
are a bit more slow and expensive,
는 조금 더 느리고 비용이 많이 듭니다,
and as less as possible, slow and expensive end-to-end tests.
그리고 가능한 한 느리고 비용이 많이 드는 종단 간 테스트를 줄입니다.
I don't think this is really relevant.
이건 별로 관련이 없는 것 같아요.
Because if I would have asked 10 people in this room,
이 방에 있는 10명에게 물어봤으면,
give me a definition of a unit test,
단위 테스트의 정의를 알려주세요,
I'd probably receive eight different ones.
아마 여덟 가지를 받을 것입니다.
Because we simply can't agree on what a unit test is.
단위 테스트가 무엇인지에 대해 동의할 수 없기 때문입니다.
And I don't want to be bogged down by conversations
그리고 대화에 얽매이고 싶지 않아요.
like, Jonas, you know, you just named this thing
조나스, 네가 방금 이걸 이름 지었잖아.
an integration test, but actually it's a component test.
통합 테스트라고 하지만 사실은 컴포넌트 테스트입니다.
Is that relevant?
관련이 있나요?
Does that help us?
도움이 되나요?
I don't think so.
아닌 것 같아.
Because the type of test is how you're doing things.
시험의 유형은 당신이 일을 하는 방식이니까.
It's technical detail.
기술적인 세부 사항입니다.
It's seldom really relevant.
실제 관련성이 거의 없습니다.
And we should try to step away from that
그리고 우리는 그것에서 벗어나려고 노력해야 합니다.
and try to step away from the classical pyramid.
고전적인 피라미드에서 벗어나려고 노력해야 합니다.
What you want to test is an integration, a behavior,
테스트하려는 것은 통합, 즉 동작입니다,
or an implementation detail.
또는 구현 세부 사항입니다.
And that's much more relevant.
훨씬 더 관련성이 높습니다.
And they also make shapes for that, the testing honeycomb.
그리고 그들은 또한 그것을 위한 모양, 테스트 벌집을 만듭니다.
Online, you'll find a different version of this thing.
온라인에서 다른 버전을 찾을 수 있어요.
And this is a slightly altered, my own custom interpretation.
그리고 이것은 약간 변형된 제 나름대로의 해석입니다.
So let's start.
그럼 시작해보죠.
For one, you can see there four layers.
우선 네 개의 레이어가 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
At the bottom, we find the static triangle.
맨 아래에는 정적 삼각형이 있습니다.
Now, what is static?
이제 정적이란 무엇일까요?
Static is your static code analyzers,
스태틱은 정적 코드 분석기입니다,
like Sonar in the Java world.
자바 세계의 소나처럼.
Then you have fewer, at the bottom,
그 다음에는 하단에 더 적습니다,
implementation detail tests.
구현 세부 테스트.
I will delve into that later.
나중에 자세히 설명하겠습니다.
And then you want to have lots of behavior tests, feature
그리고 많은 동작 테스트를 하고 싶으시겠죠.
tests, use case tests.
테스트, 사용 사례 테스트.
And that does not imply any type of test.
그리고 이것은 어떤 유형의 테스트도 의미하지 않습니다.
Also, implementation detail tests,
또한 구현 세부 테스트,
that does not imply unit tests, integration tests.
단위 테스트, 통합 테스트를 의미하지 않습니다.
It can be anything.
무엇이든 될 수 있습니다.
You can have a unit test that is an implementation detail test.
구현 세부 테스트인 단위 테스트가 있을 수 있습니다.
But you can also test an implementation detail
하지만 구현 세부 사항을 테스트할 수도 있습니다.
to an integration test.
를 통합 테스트에 추가합니다.
And the same goes for your behavior.
행동도 마찬가지입니다.
You should focus on that.
거기에 집중해야 해.
And at the top, we have integrated tests.
그리고 맨 위에는 통합 테스트가 있습니다.
Don't get confused by integration tests.
통합 테스트에 혼동하지 마세요.
An integrated test.
통합 테스트입니다.
And what is an integrated test?
통합 시험이란 무엇인가요?
An integrated test is simply a test
통합 테스트는 단순히 테스트입니다.
that runs against a real environment.
실제 환경에서 실행되는 테스트입니다.
Dev can even be production.
개발 환경도 프로덕션 환경일 수 있습니다.
Let me give you an example of an integrated test.
통합 테스트의 예를 들어보겠습니다.
In the current project I'm working on,
현재 작업 중인 프로젝트에서,
we have something called the sanity tester.
정신력 테스터라는 것이 있습니다.
We call it nicknamed the nun.
수녀라는 별명을 붙였어요.
And what this thing does, actually,
그리고 이게 하는 일은,
is when we deploy something, it fires off certain requests
우리가 무언가를 배포할 때 특정 요청을 실행합니다.
to our API and kind of smoke tests things.
를 API에 전송하고 일종의 스모크 테스트를 합니다.
And you might wonder, why would you do that?
왜 그렇게 하는지 궁금하실 겁니다.
Well, because today's world is a bit different than 10 years
글쎄요, 오늘날의 세상은 10년 전과는 조금 달라졌으니까요.
ago, right?
10년 전이죠?
In the past, we would write like this big monolithic
과거에는 이렇게 큰 모놀리식으로 작성했습니다.
applications.
응용 프로그램.
And next to it, we have like this Oracle database.
그리고 그 옆에는 다음과 같은 오라클 데이터베이스가 있습니다.
That's not true anymore.
더 이상 그렇지 않습니다.
Today's world is microservice, right?
오늘날의 세상은 마이크로서비스죠?
And that's not only it.
이뿐만이 아니에요.
Next to that, in this microservice landscape,
그 다음에는 마이크로서비스 환경에서,
we also have lots of tools floating around.
우리 주변에는 많은 도구가 떠돌고 있습니다.
I don't have the SQL database anymore.
더 이상 SQL 데이터베이스가 없습니다.
Well, I do.
난 있어.
But I also have other tools, like we use Elastic for search,
하지만 검색에 Elastic을 사용하는 것처럼 다른 도구도 있습니다,
because that's a really good tool for that.
정말 좋은 도구이기 때문입니다.
And for example, in the current project,
예를 들어 현재 프로젝트에서
we're heavily reliant on Kafka.
우리는 카프카에 크게 의존하고 있습니다.
And on Kafka, we use Avro.
그리고 카프카에서는 Avro를 사용합니다.
So we use the schema registry.
그래서 스키마 레지스트리를 사용합니다.
And what often happens is that, or sometimes, not often,
그리고 이런 일이 자주 일어나기도 하고, 자주 일어나지 않을 때도 있습니다,
but sometimes it happens, that we forget to actually apply
하지만 가끔은 실제로 적용하는 것을 잊어버리는 경우가 있습니다.
the Elasticsearch index when we deploy,
을 적용하는 것을 잊어버리는 경우가 있습니다,
because that is actually living in a separate repository.
실제로는 별도의 리포지토리에 있기 때문입니다.
It's living in one of our Terraform repositories
테라폼 저장소 중 하나에 있습니다.
away from the code.
코드에서 멀리 떨어져 있습니다.
And my code can be green.
그리고 내 코드는 녹색이 될 수 있습니다.
Like, I can have 100% code coverage.
코드 커버리지가 100%가 되는 거죠.
But still, if I deploy, things might break,
하지만 여전히 배포하면 문제가 생길 수 있습니다,
because that Terraform module has a mistake in there,
테라폼 모듈에 오류가 있기 때문이죠,
or some other services, depending on something
또는 다른 서비스에 따라
I didn't apply correctly.
제대로 신청하지 않았습니다.
Well, a sanity test, an integrated test
정신력 테스트, 통합 테스트
in your environment, might catch these things very early,
환경에서는 이런 것들을 아주 일찍 발견할 수 있습니다,
without you having to click and suddenly see,
클릭해서 갑자기 볼 필요 없이 말이죠,
like, oh, this doesn't work anymore.
아, 이건 더 이상 작동하지 않네요.
On the subject of implementation detail tests,
구현 세부 테스트 중입니다,
I would like to look at this requirement.
이 요구 사항을 살펴보고 싶습니다.
An email notification should be sent to the receiver
수신자에게 이메일 알림을 보내야 합니다.
once an invoice has been paid.
인보이스가 결제되면
It's a fairly simple requirement, right?
꽤 간단한 요구 사항이지 않나요?
And that is defined by the email service, Java interface.
그리고 그것은 이메일 서비스인 자바 인터페이스에 의해 정의됩니다.
And it's implemented by the SCS email service.
그리고 이것은 SCS 이메일 서비스에 의해 구현됩니다.
SCS, if you don't know, stands for simple email service.
SCS는 간단한 이메일 서비스의 약자입니다.
It's an AWS component you can use to send emails.
이메일을 보내는 데 사용할 수 있는 AWS 구성 요소입니다.
So in full, this thing reads, actually,
전체 내용을 보면 다음과 같습니다,
the simple email service, email service.
간단한 이메일 서비스, 이메일 서비스.
Okay, we're done.
좋아, 끝났어.
We've implemented this.
구현했습니다.
The requirement is working.
요구사항이 작동합니다.
It's deployed.
배포되었습니다.
It's being used in production.
프로덕션에 사용 중입니다.
And after a year, you get some feedback,
1년 후, 피드백을 받습니다,
and you see, actually, we thought we were gonna send out
그리고 사실, 저희는 우리가
millions of emails, but that's actually not true.
수백만 개의 이메일을 보낼 줄 알았지만 사실은 그렇지 않았습니다.
It was a false assumption.
잘못된 가정이었습니다.
We're only sending out a couple of emails a month.
우리는 한 달에 몇 개의 이메일만 발송하고 있습니다.
So that SCS service, like the cloud, is not for free, right?
클라우드처럼 SCS 서비스도 무료가 아니죠?
It's quite expensive.
꽤 비싸네요.
So maybe we should switch to that old SMTP server
그럼 이전 SMTP 서버로 전환해야겠군요.
we have here.
여기 있습니다.
Should be fine, should save us some bucks.
괜찮을 거야, 돈을 좀 절약할 수 있을 거야.
Let's do that.
그렇게 하자.
So what we do, obviously, we make an SMTP email service
그래서 우리가 하는 일은 당연히 SMTP 이메일 서비스를 만드는 것입니다.
implementation, and we switch.
구현하고 전환합니다.
And now my question goes,
이제 질문이 있습니다,
should that requirement test fail
요구 사항 테스트에 실패하면
because I made an implementation detail change?
구현 세부 사항을 변경했기 때문인가요?
No.
아니요.
And this is something to think about
그리고 이것은 생각해 볼만한 것입니다.
when you're designing your test.
테스트를 설계할 때 고려해야 할 사항입니다.
Sometimes people ask me the question, like,
가끔 사람들이 저에게 이런 질문을 합니다,
what makes a test an implementation detail test?
테스트가 구현 세부 테스트가 되는 이유는 무엇인가요?
And what makes a test a behavioral test?
무엇이 테스트를 행동 테스트로 만들까요?
Sometimes it's bloody obvious, right?
가끔은 너무 뻔하지 않나요?
But sometimes there's a very thin line,
하지만 가끔은 아주 가느다란 선이 있죠,
and the world is not black and white.
세상은 흑백이 아니에요.
It's not that simple.
그렇게 간단하지 않아요.
Another example or analogy is a little pet project of mine.
또 다른 예시 또는 비유는 제 작은 애완동물 프로젝트입니다.
Like I said, I love writing code,
앞서 말했듯이 저는 코드 작성을 좋아합니다,
so I started in the weekend writing an XML mapper.
그래서 주말에 XML 매퍼를 작성하기 시작했습니다.
Well, I first started with writing a SAX parser,
처음에는 SAX 파서를 작성하는 것부터 시작했습니다,
and now, based on that SAX parser,
그리고 이제 그 SAX 구문 분석기에 기반하여
I'm writing an XML mapper.
XML 매퍼를 작성 중입니다.
The project now is called XJX,
이제 프로젝트 이름은 XJX입니다,
but the interface, not the Java interface, obviously,
하지만 분명히 자바 인터페이스가 아닌 인터페이스입니다,
but the application interface, looks like this.
하지만 애플리케이션 인터페이스는 다음과 같습니다.
It's very simple, right?
아주 간단하죠?
It looks a bit like our Jackson object mapper,
잭슨 오브젝트 매퍼와 비슷해 보입니다,
where we give it a XML document,
여기서 XML 문서를 제공합니다,
and you say I want it to be mapped on this clause,
이 절에 매핑되기를 원한다고 말합니다,
and I'll give you the clause.
그리고 그 절을 줄게요.
And I started implementing this thing,
그리고 이걸 구현하기 시작했습니다,
and writing tests for that, focused on the behavior.
그리고 그 동작에 초점을 맞춘 테스트를 작성했습니다.
And after a while, I realized,
그리고 잠시 후 깨달았습니다,
like, nah, this ain't gonna cut it.
이건 안 되겠다 싶었죠.
I was at like 80% of something of the full implementation.
전체 구현의 80% 정도에 도달했습니다.
I thought, like, I learned a lot.
많이 배웠다고 생각했어요.
I would never do it like that,
난 절대 저렇게 안 할 거야,
and actually, I'm a bit stuck.
사실 좀 막혔어요.
I don't like this design, so what do you do?
이 디자인이 마음에 들지 않는데 어떻게 해야 하나요?
Agile way, right?
애자일 방식이죠?
You take a step back, and you learn from your mistakes.
한 발 물러서서 실수로부터 배우는 거죠.
So let's just imagine that this application
이 애플리케이션이
interface is represented by this rectangle,
인터페이스가 이 사각형으로 표시된다고 가정해 봅시다,
and the behavior is clear, right?
그리고 동작은 명확하죠?
You have some kind of input, depending on the input.
입력에 따라 어떤 종류의 입력이 있습니다.
You have some kind of output.
어떤 종류의 출력이 있습니다.
And I wrote my test against those arrows, basically.
그리고 저는 기본적으로 이 화살표에 대해 테스트를 작성했습니다.
And then you had my first implementation.
그리고 첫 번째 구현을 했죠.
And I thought, like, nah, this is not gonna work,
그리고는 이건 안 되겠구나 싶었죠,
so away with it.
그래서 그만뒀죠.
I think about 80% of the clauses I just threw away,
방금 버린 조항의 80% 정도는 버린 것 같아요,
and some 20% I decided to reuse,
그리고 약 20%는 재사용하기로 결정했습니다,
because they were useful, and I replaced it.
유용했기 때문에 교체했습니다.
And you know what happened?
그리고 무슨 일이 일어났는지 아세요?
I'm not gonna say that 100% of my tests were green.
내 테스트의 100%가 녹색이었다고 말하진 않겠습니다.
No, but 80% of my tests were green.
아니, 하지만 내 테스트의 80%가 녹색이었어.
Why?
왜?
Because I was testing against that behavior.
그 동작에 대해 테스트하고 있었기 때문입니다.
That was the most important thing.
그게 가장 중요했어요.
I was not constantly focused on testing
테스트에 계속 집중하지 못했습니다.
these individual clauses and their methods.
이러한 개별 조항과 그 방법.
They're, in a way, ephemeral.
어떤 의미에서는 일시적인 것입니다.
And that 20% that failed,
그리고 실패한 20%,
that was because I was testing some implementation detail
구현 세부 사항을 테스트하고 있었기 때문입니다.
that changed.
변경되었습니다.
And also, along the way, I decided to change
그리고 그 과정에서 다음과 같이 변경하기로 결정했습니다.
the behavior a bit, some annotation that had another meaning.
동작을 약간 변경하고 다른 의미를 가진 주석을 달았습니다.
Another analogy I like to use is one from Mim Delvois.
제가 좋아하는 또 다른 비유는 밈 델보아의 비유입니다.
Mim Delvois is an artist, and he makes art installations.
밈 델보아는 예술가이며 설치미술을 합니다.
And this one is called the cloaca.
그리고 이것은 배설물이라고 불립니다.
And it's actually the name of the ancient sewer in Rome.
사실 로마의 고대 하수도의 이름입니다.
And what does the cloaca do?
배설물은 무엇을 할까요?
Well, there's no other way to put it.
글쎄요, 달리 표현할 방법이 없네요.
The alternative name is the shit-making machine, basically,
다른 이름은 똥 만드는 기계입니다,
the poo machine, because the behavior of this thing
똥 기계, 왜냐하면 이 물건의 행동이
is simple.
간단합니다.
You put in a sandwich at one end, and at the other end,
한쪽 끝과 다른 쪽 끝에 샌드위치를 넣습니다,
yeah, shit comes out, feces come out.
그래, 똥이 나오고, 똥이 나온다.
That's what he made.
저렇게 만들었어.
He made different versions of this thing,
그는 이걸 다른 버전으로 만들었어,
some more dark and grim.
좀 더 어둡고 암울하게.
But the behavior is clear, right?
하지만 행동은 분명하죠?
He replicated the human digestive system, in a way.
어떤 면에서는 인간의 소화기관을 복제했어.
But just imagine that you're testing all individual modules,
하지만 모든 개별 모듈을 테스트하고 있다고 상상해 보세요,
all individual tubes and pumps and whatnot, and connections.
모든 개별 튜브와 펌프, 그리고 연결부를 테스트한다고 상상해 보세요.
Those would be, in a way, implementation details.
어떻게 보면 구현 세부 사항이라고 할 수 있죠.
But if one of those pumps breaks down
하지만 그 펌프 중 하나가 고장나면
because your initial design was not good enough,
초기 설계가 충분하지 않았기 때문이죠,
and you replace it, what do you want to fail
그리고 그것을 교체하면, 무엇을 실패하고 싶습니까?
when you replace it with a better version?
더 나은 버전으로 교체하면?
That behavior is still the same, right?
그 동작은 여전히 동일하죠?
So how do we put this all into code?
그럼 이 모든 것을 어떻게 코드로 표현할까요?
We already discussed why we write tests, right?
테스트를 작성하는 이유에 대해서는 이미 설명했죠?
Change, evolvability.
변화, 진화 가능성.
What do we test?
무엇을 테스트할까요?
Behavior, and to a lesser extent, code,
행동, 그리고 그보다 더 적은 범위의 코드,
implementation details.
구현 세부 사항.
So how do we put this all into code?
이 모든 것을 어떻게 코드에 넣을까요?
And the first thing to note is that we're developers, right?
가장 먼저 주목해야 할 것은 우리가 개발자라는 사실입니다.
And the first thing to note is that tests and production code
그리고 가장 먼저 주목해야 할 것은 테스트와 프로덕션 코드가
are actually different things.
는 실제로 다른 것입니다.
They live in different packages,
서로 다른 패키지에 살고 있습니다,
different contexts, and different rules.
다른 상황과 다른 규칙에 살고 있습니다.
You should not treat them in a way equal.
그들을 동등하게 취급해서는 안 됩니다.
To give an example, avoid abstractions.
예를 들자면, 추상화를 피하세요.
This is something we do for the right reasons
이것은 우리가 올바른 이유로 하는 일입니다.
in our production code.
프로덕션 코드에서.
We constantly make abstractions, polymorphism,
우리는 끊임없이 추상화, 다형성을 만듭니다,
hide things behind interfaces.
인터페이스 뒤에 사물을 숨깁니다.
But we should not do that too much in our test code
하지만 테스트 코드에서 너무 많이 해서는 안 됩니다.
if we value the documentation value of our tests.
테스트의 문서화 값을 중요하게 생각한다면 말이죠.
You want to keep your readers in your method,
독자를 메서드에 계속 머물게 하려고 합니다,
and you want to minimize the setup and teardown logic
그리고 설정 및 해체 로직을 최소화하고 싶습니다.
to only the technical.
를 기술적인 부분으로만 변경합니다.
If I'm reading a test method,
테스트 메서드를 읽고 있는 경우,
and you force me to jump out of that method
그 메서드에서 뛰어내리라고 강요합니다.
all the way to the top of the clause,
절의 맨 위까지,
and then trace it to the bottom of the clause,
를 찾은 다음 절의 맨 아래까지 추적합니다,
I'm going to be in a bad situation.
안 좋은 상황에 처하게 되겠군요.
I'm going to jump out of that method
그 방법에서 뛰어내릴 거야.
all the way to the top of the clause,
절의 맨 위까지 이동합니다,
and then trace back to that test method.
그리고 해당 테스트 메서드로 거슬러 올라갑니다.
And if there are 20 tests in that clause,
그리고 해당 절에 20개의 테스트가 있는 경우,
I already forgot which one it was.
어떤 테스트인지 벌써 잊어버렸네요.
Or I'm reading a test method,
아니면 테스트 방법을 읽고 있어요,
and you force me down a trail of method calls
메서드 호출의 흔적을 따라가도록 강요합니다.
just to find out why a value is being set in a certain way,
값이 특정 방식으로 설정되는 이유를 알아내기 위해서입니다,
and then have to trace back,
그리고 역추적해야 합니다,
only to be led in another direction.
다른 방향으로 유도됩니다.
That doesn't help me.
도움이 안 돼요.
You want to communicate clearly.
명확하게 의사소통하고 싶어요.
You want to document.
문서화하고 싶습니다.
You want to be in that method.
그 메서드에 들어가고 싶습니다.
The cyclomatic complexity of a test should be one.
테스트의 순환 복잡도는 1이어야 합니다.
That basically means avoid ifs.
이는 기본적으로 if를 피하라는 뜻입니다.
I'm pretty sure you can go without ifs.
ifs 없이도 갈 수 있을 것 같네요.
If you need an if,
if가 필요하다면,
you probably need two tests.
두 개의 테스트가 필요할 것입니다.
And avoid loops.
그리고 루프를 피하세요.
Loops you sometimes need.
가끔 필요한 루프.
But you really want to avoid them.
하지만 정말 피하고 싶을 때.
You want to keep it simple in your tests.
테스트를 단순하게 유지하고 싶어요.
On the subject of test method naming,
테스트 방법 명명에 관한 주제,
what we often do is we take the clause
우리가 종종 하는 것은 우리가 종종 하는 것은
and we just put the suffix test behind it.
뒤에 접미사 테스트를 넣습니다.
That's fine for implementation detail tests
구현 세부 테스트에는 괜찮습니다.
like the SES email service test.
SES 이메일 서비스 테스트처럼.
Makes sense, right?
말이 되죠?
But what if we apply a different pattern here?
하지만 여기에 다른 패턴을 적용하면 어떨까요?
One that we actually already know.
우리가 이미 알고 있는 패턴입니다.
One that I learned from the Screaming Architecture ideas.
비명을 지르는 건축 아이디어에서 배운 것입니다.
Screaming Architecture is about
비명을 지르는 건축은
that your codebase screams the domain to you.
코드베이스가 도메인을 비명을 지르는 시간입니다.
Not the technical stuff.
기술적인 문제가 아닙니다.
In the same way,
같은 방식으로,
I think it's valuable if our test clauses
테스트 절이 다음과 같다면 가치가 있다고 생각합니다.
scream the behavior at you.
동작을 비명을 지르면
If they're behavioral tests, of course.
물론 행동 테스트인 경우.
Because an invoice service test doesn't tell me much.
인보이스 서비스 테스트는 많은 것을 알려주지 않으니까요.
I know it's probably backed by a test.
아마도 테스트에 의해 뒷받침되고 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
But it's not a test.
하지만 테스트가 아닙니다.
I know it's probably backed by an invoice service.
아마도 인보이스 서비스에 의해 뒷받침되는 것 같습니다.
Hooray.
만세!
Bad example, a pay invoice feature test.
나쁜 예, 결제 인보이스 기능 테스트.
Yeah, you can pay an invoice.
네, 인보이스를 결제할 수 있습니다.
Who would have guessed that, right?
누가 상상이나 했겠어요?
But if I had something like this
하지만 이런 게 있었다면
and I was browsing through the test packages
테스트 패키지를 살펴보고 있었는데
and clicked it open and I saw
를 클릭하고 열었더니
a list of those things that actually describe the behavior.
실제로 동작을 설명하는 목록이 표시됩니다.
This tells me so much more.
이것은 훨씬 더 많은 것을 말해줍니다.
And you may not like the feature test suffix.
기능 테스트 접미사가 마음에 들지 않을 수도 있습니다.
I know it's quite lengthy and you repeat yourself.
꽤 길고 반복하는 거 알아요.
But that's not the gist of it.
하지만 그게 요점이 아니에요.
The thing is that it actually screams the behavior at you.
문제는 실제로 당신에게 비명을 지른다는 겁니다.
And when we open such a test clause
그리고 그런 테스트 절을 열면
and look at the test methods,
테스트 메서드를 살펴봅시다,
what I often find is
제가 자주 발견하는 것은
and I did it myself constantly,
그리고 나는 그것을 계속했다,
that I describe what I am testing.
내가 테스트하는 것을 설명합니다.
Here are two examples of what test.
다음은 두 가지 테스트의 예입니다.
Test expire invoice.
인보이스 만료 테스트.
And then I wonder what happens actually
그리고 실제로 어떤 일이 일어나는지 궁금합니다.
when an invoice expires.
인보이스가 만료될 때
I really, you force me to read that method
정말, 그 방법을 읽으라고 강요하는군요.
just to understand the behavior
그냥 행동을 이해하려고
of an invoice expiring.
인보이스 만료 시간
Or the last one,
또는 마지막 송장,
add pineapple topping to pizza test.
피자 테스트에 파인애플 토핑을 추가합니다.
Now I wonder, I hope it's not allowed.
이젠 안 되겠네.
I don't know.
모르겠어.
You force me to read this method.
이 방법을 읽으라고 강요하는군요.
And yes, in a way they're trivial examples.
네, 어떤 면에서는 사소한 예시입니다.
But I can't put complex examples on the slides.
하지만 슬라이드에 복잡한 예제를 넣을 수는 없죠.
But what you want to do is not
하지만 당신이 하고 싶은 것은
what you're testing.
테스트하는 것이 아닙니다.
You want to describe why the test is there.
테스트의 이유를 설명합니다.
Because the why captures the behavior.
이유는 동작을 포착하기 때문입니다.
So if I would have rewritten those two tests,
따라서 이 두 테스트를 다시 작성했다면,
I would have written something like
다음과 같이 작성했을 것입니다.
an unexpired invoice should expire automatically
만료되지 않은 인보이스는 자동으로 만료되어야 합니다.
after 30 days of the publication date.
발행일로부터 30일 후
And notice something.
그리고 주목하세요.
There are underscores there.
밑줄이 있습니다.
I would never do that in production code.
프로덕션 코드에서는 절대 그렇게 하지 않습니다.
That's not the Java way.
그건 자바 방식이 아닙니다.
But I really, I'm a bit dyslexic.
근데 나 진짜 난독증이 좀 심해.
So it helps me if I
그래서 다음과 같이 하면 도움이 됩니다.
split things up into logical blocks.
논리적 블록으로 나누면 도움이 됩니다.
And an underscore really helps.
밑줄은 정말 도움이 됩니다.
Because this is a rather short test method.
이것은 다소 짧은 테스트 방법이기 때문입니다.
Sometimes they're even longer
때로는 더 길기도 합니다.
if I really want to describe it.
굳이 설명하자면
Or the last one.
아니면 마지막 하나.
Pineapple is an illegal topping, luckily.
다행히 파인애플은 불법 토핑입니다.
And should prevent the cook from adding it.
그리고 요리사가 파인애플을 넣지 못하게 해야 합니다.
I know the behavior.
동작을 알아냈습니다.
I know what's going on.
무슨 일인지 알아.
I don't even need to read the contents of the method.
메서드의 내용을 읽을 필요도 없어.
You want to avoid giving examples
예제를 제공하지 않으려는 경우
in your test method names.
을 테스트 메서드 이름에 포함시키지 않아야 합니다.
And here is an example of a test
다음은 테스트의 예입니다.
or a set of tests that give examples.
또는 예제를 제공하는 테스트 집합입니다.
Should consider ABC as a weak password.
ABC를 약한 비밀번호로 간주해야 합니다.
The second one is slightly better
두 번째가 조금 더 낫습니다.
because I already know why it's weak.
왜 약한지 이미 알고 있으니까요.
Should consider ABC as a too short password.
ABC는 너무 짧은 비밀번호라고 생각해야 합니다.
But then I question like,
하지만 다음과 같이 질문합니다,
OK, is ABC this?
좋아, 이게 ABC인가?
And then I ask myself,
그리고 스스로에게 묻습니다,
OK, is ABC this?
좋아, 이게 ABC인가?
And then I ask myself,
그리고 스스로에게 묻습니다,
OK, is ABCD then not too short?
그렇다면 ABCD는 너무 짧지 않은가?
I don't know the rules at play here.
여기서 어떤 규칙이 적용되는지 모르겠어요.
And this is something we constantly do.
그리고 이것은 우리가 끊임없이 하는 일입니다.
And I'm doing it myself too.
그리고 저도 하고 있습니다.
Because you're so focused
넌 너무 집중하니까
on implementing it
구현하는 데에
you just quickly write the name down.
이름을 빠르게 적으면 됩니다.
And we never
그리고 우리는 절대
step back to the test method name.
테스트 메서드 이름으로 돌아갑니다.
But sometimes if I look
하지만 가끔은
at the test method names I wrote a month ago
한 달 전에 작성한 테스트 방법 이름을 보면
without really being
실제로 존재하지 않고
attentive to it,
주의 깊게,
I keep finding myself writing stuff like that.
자꾸 이런 글을 쓰게 되네요.
What you want to do
하고 싶은 일
is avoid giving examples.
예시를 들지 않는 것입니다.
So let's rewrite those two test method names.
이제 이 두 테스트 메서드 이름을 다시 작성해 봅시다.
You want to, again,
다시 한 번
focus on the behavior.
행동에 집중하세요.
Should consider passwords too short
비밀번호가 너무 짧은 것을 고려해야 함
when having a length, again, underscores
길이가 길면 다시 밑줄을 긋습니다.
I want to make it clear
명확히 하고 싶습니다.
of 8 or less.
8 이하로
And the way I would have written it is the last one.
그리고 제가 썼을 방식이 마지막 방식입니다.
Just simply, minimum length
그냥 간단하게, 최소 길이
of a password is 8. That's it.
암호의 최소 길이는 8입니다. 그게 다입니다.
That's clear.
이제 명확해졌습니다.
And if you want to document
그리고 문서화하려면
your code, if you want your
코드를 원한다면
test code to have any kind of documentation
모든 종류의 문서가 있는 테스트 코드
value, you really
가치, 정말
should focus on
에 집중해야 합니다.
communicating clearly.
명확하게 소통해야 합니다.
Remember what I said
내가 한 말 기억하기
in the beginning
처음에
of this section, avoid abstractions?
이 섹션의 추상화를 피하는 방법은?
Well, we should
글쎄, 그래야지
also embrace magic numbers.
마법의 숫자도 받아들여야 합니다.
I would never
나는 절대
embrace magic numbers and strings
마법의 숫자와 문자열을 포용하다
in my production code. You put that in constants, right?
를 프로덕션 코드에 넣었습니다. 상수에 넣었죠?
High above the class.
클래스보다 높습니다.
Well, in test codes
테스트 코드에서
different context, different rules.
다른 컨텍스트, 다른 규칙.
Let's look at the following
다음을 살펴봅시다.
test. So we
test. 그래서 우리는
have a VAT calculator and we
부가가치세 계산기가 있고
get some VAT amount out of there
부가가치세 금액을 계산합니다.
or calculate it.
또는 계산합니다.
But the important thing is the
하지만 중요한 것은
yellow constants.
노란색 상수입니다.
I do all this based on a gross
이 모든 작업은 총
price and a VAT percentage
가격 및 부가가치세 비율
and I expect some amount out of there.
그리고 나는 거기에서 어느 정도 금액을 기대합니다.
And then I run the test and suddenly
그리고 테스트를 실행하니 갑자기
I see something like, expected 21
예상 21과 같은 것이 표시됩니다.
but was 22.
하지만 22였습니다.
And I have no idea where these values are coming from.
이 값의 출처가 어디인지 전혀 모르겠습니다.
If I open the test, you again force me
테스트를 열면 다시 강제로
away out of the test.
테스트에서 벗어납니다.
In tests
테스트 중
you want to embrace magic numbers.
마법의 숫자를 받아들이고 싶을 때
You want to avoid all kind of, even the simplest
당신은 모든 종류의, 심지어 가장 단순한 것조차도 피하고 싶어합니다.
layers of abstraction and just put
추상화 레이어를 추가하고
numbers there.
숫자를 넣습니다.
Because it's so obvious
너무 뻔하니까
to immediately spot what this test is about
이 테스트가 무엇인지 즉시 알아차리기 위해
and undoing. Of course
그리고 취소합니다. 물론
the
그리고
tax amount of 121
세금 금액 121
21% of tax is 21.
세금의 21%는 21.
For the last
마지막
section of this talk, I would like us
이 강연의 섹션에서, 나는 우리가
to look together at the following test.
다음 테스트를 함께 살펴보겠습니다.
It's again around invoices
다시 인보이스 관련 테스트입니다.
and
그리고
first
if we want to test an invoice, we need an invoice.
인보이스를 테스트하려면 인보이스가 필요합니다.
Right? So to need an invoice
그렇죠? 따라서 인보이스가 필요하려면
you need to have a billing address apparently
청구서 주소가 있어야 합니다.
and a shipping address and you need to have some
그리고 배송 주소가 있어야 하며
kind of items in there and a customer.
종류의 품목과 고객이 있어야 합니다.
And then we finally have
그리고 마침내
this invoice.
이 인보이스입니다.
And then we get the VAT amount out of there
그리고 거기서 부가가치세 금액을 가져옵니다.
and then we just say it needs to meet
그런 다음 다음을 충족해야 한다고 말합니다.
42. Well that's fairly simple
42. 아주 간단합니다.
right? Because if you look again at the yellow numbers
맞죠? 노란색 숫자를 다시 보면
yeah, 21 plus 21
네, 21 더하기 21
is 42 right? Simple.
42가 맞나요? 간단하죠.
But this is a pattern that we're constantly
하지만 이것은 우리가 끊임없이 반복하는 패턴입니다.
doing.
하고 있습니다.
It's having big
그것은 큰
chunks in our given
주어진 청크에
part. Because if you want
부분입니다. 왜냐하면 원한다면
to prove this test, the first thing
이 테스트를 증명하려면 먼저
to note is that a good test exists
주목해야 할 것은 좋은 테스트가 존재한다는 것입니다.
out of three parts.
세 부분 중
Given, When, Then. Arrange, Act,
주어진, 언제, 그때. 배열, 행동,
Assert. That's the first
Assert. 이것이 첫 번째
thing I think about when writing a test. What is my
테스트를 작성할 때 가장 먼저 생각하는 것입니다. 내
given? What is my when? What is my then?
주어진? 나의 때는 무엇인가요? 내 그때는 무엇입니까?
And when I have identified them
그리고 내가 그들을 확인했을 때
I make
나는
three blocks in my code. I don't want like this
내 코드에 세 블록이 있습니다. 이렇게 하고 싶지 않습니다.
big wall of text.
텍스트의 큰 벽.
Obviously the given part and the assert part
분명히 주어진 부분과 어서스트 부분
are at the top and the bottom but sometimes
는 위와 아래에 있지만 때로는
I need to scan what is actually being tested. I need to
실제로 테스트 중인 것을 스캔해야 합니다. 나는
find that one method.
그 방법을 찾아야 합니다.
But just visually dividing it
하지만 시각적으로 나누기만 하면
and adding little comments, that's what I like
그리고 작은 주석을 추가하는 것, 그게 제가 좋아하는 것입니다.
to do, makes it clear.
해야 할 일이 명확해집니다.
Well we
그럼 우리
can even improve on that I think.
더 개선할 수 있을 것 같아요.
Because that first part
왜냐하면 첫 번째 부분
is quite lengthy and actually all we
꽤 길고 실제로 우리가
care about for this test is
이 테스트에서 신경쓰는 것은
the invoice
인보이스
items.
And this is something I
그리고 이것은 내가
do a lot. Like let's
많이 하죠. 예를 들어
just imagine this is the first invoice test
이것이 첫 번째 인보이스 테스트라고 상상해 보세요.
I wrote and this is the first one.
내가 썼고 이것이 첫 번째입니다.
And I'm done and I need to write my second one.
이제 끝났고 두 번째 글을 써야겠어요.
What do I do?
어떻게 해야 하지?
Copy and paste.
복사해서 붙여넣으세요.
Right? And then I just alter some
멋지지 않나요? 그리고 일부만 변경합니다.
other values in there and I keep on repeating
다른 값을 넣고 계속 반복합니다.
and doing that and my colleague will do the same.
그렇게 하면 제 동료도 똑같이 할 것입니다.
And when I open that
그리고 제가 저걸 열면
invoice service test class, what do I
인보이스 서비스 테스트 클래스, 어떻게 해야 하나요?
find? Lots and lots of text.
찾았나요? 많은 텍스트가 있습니다.
And it's all
그리고 이게 다야
clutter. What you
클러터. 당신
want to do is apply
하고 싶은 일
something like the object model pattern.
객체 모델 패턴과 같은 것입니다.
I wrote a small blog post about that
이에 대한 작은 블로그 포스팅을 작성했습니다.
if you want to dive deeper into it.
더 자세히 알아보고 싶으시다면요.
But what
하지만
object model allows you to do
객체 모델을 사용하면 할 수 있는 작업은
and it's a pattern from Martin Fowler so
그리고 이것은 마틴 파울러의 패턴이므로
it's definitely great.
정말 멋지네요.
It allows us to
다음을 수행할 수 있습니다.
emphasize on what matters and hide
중요한 것을 강조하고 숨기기
all the irrelevant stuff.
모든 관련 없는 것들.
And that
그리고 그
previous chunk, that given chunk
이전 청크, 주어진 청크
now looks like this.
이제 이렇게 보입니다.
You may not
다음과 같이
some colleagues say I don't like
어떤 동료들은 내가 싫어한다고 한다.
mother as a suffix. I don't know. I like my
어머니를 접미사로 쓰는 걸 좋아하지 않아요. 모르겠어요. 나는 내
mother so I use it.
어머니를 좋아해서 사용합니다.
So you start with that
그래서 그걸로 시작합니다.
object that you want to build and me use
당신이 만들고 싶은 객체와 내가 사용할
mother a lot. So because the pattern
어머니를 많이 사용합니다. 따라서 패턴이
is called the same way so why not?
도 같은 방식으로 호출되므로 왜 안 될까요?
And then you give it a static factory method.
그리고 정적 팩토리 메서드를 제공합니다.
And that does not simply
그리고 그것은 단순히
return an invoice.
인보이스를 반환합니다.
It's not something that
그것은 무언가가 아닙니다
some people call a generator. No.
어떤 사람들은 발전기라고 부르죠. 아니요.
It returns a builder.
빌더를 반환합니다.
And it doesn't stop there.
그리고 거기서 멈추지 않습니다.
It returns a pre-filled
미리 채워진
builder that allows
빌더를 반환합니다.
you to overwrite what is
를 덮어쓸 수 있는
irrelevant. That's very important.
무의미합니다. 아주 중요합니다.
I'm just saying invoice mother
그냥 인보이스 어머니
gave me a valid invoice
유효한 인보이스를 주었다
and I want to just change the invoice
인보이스만 변경하고 싶습니다.
items because that's relevant for my test.
항목이 제 테스트와 관련이 있기 때문입니다.
The shipping address, all the
배송 주소, 모든
other stuff that is like mandatory for your object
객체에 필수적인 다른 것들
is already default, has default stuff
이미 기본값이고, 기본값이 있습니다.
you don't need to worry about it.
걱정할 필요가 없습니다.
And then you can happily copy paste that
그런 다음 행복하게 복사하여 붙여넣을 수 있습니다.
and remove whatever you need or don't need.
그리고 필요하거나 불필요한 부분을 제거하면 됩니다.
When I'm applying
신청할 때
this pattern in codebases what I often see
코드베이스에서 자주 볼 수 있는 패턴은 다음과 같습니다.
colleagues do is the following.
동료들이 하는 일은 다음과 같습니다.
And then I realize they didn't
그리고 그들이
understand it really. They're
정말 이해하지 못한다는 걸요. 그들은
adding these static factory methods.
이 정적 팩토리 메서드를 추가합니다.
They call them sometimes in the POS team
POS 팀에서 가끔 호출합니다.
they call them generators.
그들은 그들을 발전기라고 부른다.
No, you want to limit it.
아니, 제한하고 싶어.
You only need a couple of
두 개만 필요합니다.
static factory methods and then you
정적 팩토리 메서드만 있으면 됩니다.
just overwrite what you need.
필요한 것만 덮어쓰면 됩니다.
So for example, the
예를 들어
second one, valid invoice with
두 번째 송장, 유효한 송장
US shipping address, if you want that
미국 배송 주소, 원하는 경우
no, you just start with a valid invoice
아니요, 유효한 인보이스로 시작하세요.
and you
그리고 당신
overwrite the shipping address.
배송 주소를 덮어씁니다.
And there's a neat little trick you
그리고 깔끔한 트릭이 하나 있습니다.
can do with a
할 수 있는
Java util consumer
자바 활용 소비자
but that's in my blog.
하지만 그건 제 블로그에 있습니다.
But this makes it clear.
하지만 이렇게 하면 명확해집니다.
So you really avoid
그래서 당신은 정말로
static factory methods.
정적 팩토리 메서드.
So that
그래서
previous test, that
이전 테스트, 그
junking test now looks like this.
정크 테스트는 이제 다음과 같이 보입니다.
Change is
변경 사항은
inevitable and that is why
피할 수 없는 이유
we test. We want to adapt. We want to
우리는 테스트합니다. 우리는 적응하고 싶습니다. 우리는 원한다.
evolve our software.
소프트웨어를 발전시킵니다.
Lots of things change, not only requirements.
요구 사항뿐만 아니라 많은 것이 변합니다.
And we want
그리고 우리는
to test behavior and to a lesser
동작을 테스트하고
extent our code implementation details.
범위로 코드 구현 세부 사항을 변경합니다.
And we need to accept that
그리고 우리는 그것을 받아들여야 합니다.
tests live in different contexts and
테스트는 서로 다른 컨텍스트에서 실행되고
that is how we should test things.
이것이 바로 우리가 테스트해야 하는 방식입니다.
Test and production
테스트 및 생산
code should be
코드는 다음과 같아야 합니다.
equal citizens in your code base.
코드베이스에서 동등한 시민.
They looked at from
다음에서 살펴본
different contexts and with
다른 컨텍스트와 함께
equal architectural rights
동등한 건축 권리
cared for equally.
평등하게 돌봄.
Equally important.
똑같이 중요.
And actually, I don't agree.
사실 저는 동의하지 않습니다.
Because I think that tests are actually much
왜냐하면 저는 테스트가 실제로 훨씬
more important than your production code.
프로덕션 코드보다 더 중요하다고 생각하기 때문입니다.
Without tests you cannot evolve
테스트 없이는 진화할 수 없습니다.
that production code.
그 프로덕션 코드.
So our emphasis should be really on the tests.
따라서 테스트에 중점을 두어야 합니다.
Thanks for listening.
들어주셔서 감사합니다.